Guide to the Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Historical Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walter L. Pforzheimer collection of historical manuscripts
1370-1960
1500-1830
GEN MSS 838
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.26
(11 boxes)
The Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Historical Manuscripts contains approximately 500 manuscript documents, circa 1370s-1870s, consisting of letters, legal documents, and other manuscripts written or signed by European heads of state, government, diplomatic, military or church officials, or literary authors. Most materials are French, including documents signed by French royalty and nobility, 14th-18th centuries. Many French manuscripts date from the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars, including printed Revolutionary government documents completed in manuscript. A small amount of similar documents from other European countries and the United States are present. Some documents contain evidence of previous ownership, such as annotations, collectors' bindings, or bookplates. Also present are materials relating to Pforzheimer's research and collecting, 1920s-circa 1960s, consisting of card files, biographical notes, engraved portraits, and vendor descriptions.
Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter L. Pforzheimer, 1959-2003.
Conditions Governing Access
Restricted pending full processing. Access to specific items may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Walter L. Pforzheimer Papers (GEN MSS 817)
Walter L. Pforzheimer collection of Frank Richard Stockton (YCAL MSS 560)
Walter L. Pforzheimer (1914-2003)
Walter L. Pforzheimer, lawyer, intelligence officer, and book collector. Pforzheimer was born in Port Chester, New York, in 1914, and graduated from Yale College (1935) and Yale Law School (1938). Pforzheimer began his intelligence career in the United States Army, 1942-1945, in the Office of Strategic Services and as an Army Air Force intelligence officer. He was one of the founders of the Central Intelligence Agency in 1946, and as a CIA legislative counsel and liaison to Congress assisted in drafting the 1947 National Security Act. In 1956, he founded the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, which he curated until his retirement in 1974. In retirement, he continued to work for the CIA and taught at the Defense Intelligence College. Pforzheimer died in Washington, D.C., in 2003.
Pforzheimer came from a family of book collectors: his father, also named Walter Pforzheimer (1883-1955), collected French armorial bindings and assembled a virtually complete collection of Molière; his uncle Carl H. Pforzheimer (1879-1957) collected Percy Bysshe Shelley and his circle. Pforzheimer inherited and augmented his father's collections, and assembled his own collection of American novelist Frank Richard Stockton. In addition to curating the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, Pforzheimer built a personal collection of books and manuscripts documenting the history of military intelligence. Elected to the Yale Library Associates board of trustees in 1936, Pforzheimer was a life-long trustee and donor to the Yale Libraries. He donated his book and manuscript collections of Molière, French armorial bindings, Frank Richard Stockton, and military intelligence to the Beinecke Library in 2001.
Sources:
Peake, Hayden B. "Walter Pforzheimer -- Lawyer, Intelligence Officer, Bibliophile." In: In the Name of Intelligence: Essays in Honor of Walter Pforzheimer (Washington: NIBC Press, c1994).
"Walter L. Pforzheimer, CIA's First Curator, Dies at 88." Washington Post (2003 February 12).
Scope and Contents
The Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Historical Manuscripts contains approximately 500 manuscript documents, circa 1370s-1870s, consisting of letters, legal documents, and other manuscripts written or signed by European heads of state, government, diplomatic, military or church officials, or literary authors. Most materials are French, including documents signed by French royalty and nobility, 14th-18th centuries. Many French manuscripts date from the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars, including printed Revolutionary government documents completed in manuscript. A small amount of similar documents from other European countries and the United States are present. Some documents contain evidence of previous ownership, such as annotations, collectors' bindings, or bookplates. Also present are materials relating to Pforzheimer's research and collecting, 1920s-circa 1960s, consisting of card files, biographical notes, engraved portraits, and vendor descriptions.
Research strengths include European government, politics, and wars, 14th-19th centuries, especially France, the French Revolution, and Napoleonic Wars; manuscript collecting; and the formation of Pforzheimer's book and manuscript collections.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: November 2000 Acquisition, July 2005 Acquisitions, and Other Acquisitions.
Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Europe -- Politics and government; France -- Politics and government; France -- History -- 14th century; France -- History -- 15th century; France -- History -- 16th century; France -- History -- 17th century; France -- History -- 18th century; France -- History -- 19th century; France -- History -- Bourbons, 1589-1789; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799; Louis, King of France, XIV, 1638-1715; Louis, King of France, XV, 1710-1774; Louis, King of France, XVI, 1754-1793; Marie Antoinette, Queen, consort of Louis XVI, King of France, 1755-1793; Napoleon, Emperor of the French, I, 1769-1821; Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003
- November 2000 Acquisition, circa 1370-1960s; 4.05; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three groups: Historical Manuscripts, arranged alphabetically by name; Historical Manuscripts, Unidentified, arranged alphabetically by nationality, and chronologically within nationality; and Research Material.
  Scope and Contents
  Names indicate authors or signers of manuscripts, with a few exceptions indicated in folder notes. Name forms and dates of birth and death conform to Library of Congress authorities, except where indicated by brackets. Dates of manuscripts are indicated only if birth and death dates are lacking or unverified. Additional manuscripts pertaining to some names may be found among unidentified materials.
  In addition to contents of the Research Material subseries, some typed transcripts, English translations, and other research materials are filed with individual manuscripts. Card files are unarranged, and include cards pertaining to Pforzheimer's collections of military intelligence and Molière.
  - Historical Manuscripts
    - Adam, Juliette (1836-1936) (Box 1)
    - Adélaïde, Madame (1732-1800) (Box 1)
    - Aiguillon, Armand de Vignerot du Plessis de Richelieu, duc d' (1761-1800) (Box 1)
    - [Allix, Lieutenant General], 1831 August 30 (Box 1)
    - Alma-Tadema, Lawrence, Sir (1836-1912) (Box 1)
    - Anjou, François, duc d' (1554-1584) (Box 1)
    - Anna, Archduchess, consort of Ferdinand Charles, Archduke of Austria (1616-1676) (Box 1)
    - Anne, Queen, consort of Louis XIII, King of France (1601-1666) (Box 1)
    - [Argencé, d'], 1714 September 14 (Box 1)
    - Argenson, René-Louis de Voyer, marquis d' (1694-1757) (Box 1)
    - Avril, Paul (1843-1904) (Box 1)
    - Barthélemy, J.-J. (Jean-Jacques) (1716-1795) (Box 1)
    - [Bassy], 1635 October 29 (Box 1)
    - Beaufort, François de Bourbon, duc de (1616-1669) (Box 1)
    - Beauharnais, Eugène de (1781-1824) (Box 1)
    - [Beauvillier, Marie de, Abesse de Montmartre], 1602, 1644 (Box 1)
    - [Begon, Michael], 1647 (Box 1)
    - [Belle, Charles August Foucquet, duc de], [circa 1700] (Box 1)
    - Bellegarde, Roger de Saint-Lary, duc de (1563-1646) (Box 1)
    - Bernis, François-Joachim de Pierre de (1715-1794) (Box 1)
    - Berzelius, Jöns Jakob, friherre (1779-1848) (Box 1)
    - Blanc, Louis (1811-1882) (Box 1)
    - Bonaparte, Lucien, prince de Canino (1775-1840) (Box 1)
    - Bonaparte, Napoléon-Joseph-Charles-Paul, Prince (1822-1891) (Box 1)
    - Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne (1627-1704) (Box 1)
    - [Bourbon], undated (Box 1)
    - Bourbon, Catherine de, duchesse de Bar (1558-1604) (Box 1)
    - [Bourbon, Francois de]
    - [Bourbon, Louis Auguste de, duc du Maine (1670-1736)], 1707 August 3 (Box 1)
    - [Bourbon, Louis Auguste de, prince de Dombes (1700-1755)], 1744 November 8 (Box 1)
    - Bourbon, Louis Jean-Marie de, duc de Penthièvre (1725-1793) (Box 1)
    - Breteuil, Louis-Auguste Le Tonnelier, baron de (1730-1807) (Box 1)
    - [Bruet], 1883 (Box 1)
    - [Brughe], 1899 December 10 (Box 1)
    - Buffon, Georges Louis Leclerc, comte de (1707-1788) (Box 1)
    - Bussy, Roger de Rabutin, comte de (1618-1693) (Box 1)
    - Calonne, Charles Alexandre de (1734-1802) (Box 1)
    - Cambacérès, Jean Jacques Régis de (1753-1824) (Box 1)
    - Cambon, Jules (1845-1935) (Box 1)
    - [Campan, Genet], 1806 December 12 (Box 1)
    - Catherine de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of France (1519-1589) (Box 1)
    - Charles, d'Orléans (1394-1465)
    - Charles III, Duke of Lorraine (1543-1608) (Box 1)
    - Charles V, King of France (1338-1380)
    - Charles VI, King of France (1368-1422)
    - Charles VIII, King of France (1470-1498)
    - Charles IX, King of France (1550-1574) (Box 1)
    - Charles X, King of France (1757-1836) (Box 1)
    - Chastenay, Madame de (Victorine) (1771-1855) (Box 1)
    - Chauvelin, Bernard-François, marquis de (1766-1832) (Box 1)
    - Choiseul, Etienne-François, duc de (1719-1785) (Box 1)
    - Claretie, Jules (1840-1913) (Box 1)
    - Clèves, Marie de (1426-1487)
    - Coigny, Marie-François-Henri de Franquetot, duc de (1737-1821) (Box 1)
    - Colbert, Jean Baptiste (1619-1683) (Box 1)
    - Condé, Henri I de Bourbon, prince de (1552-1588) (Box 1)
    - Condé, Henri II de Bourbon, prince de (1588-1646) (Box 1)
    - [Condé, Henri Jules de Bourbon, prince de (1643-1709)], 1695 April 23 (Box 1)
    - Condé, Louis, prince de (1530-1569)
    - Condé, Louis, prince de (1621-1686)
    - [Condé, Louis Henri de Bourbon, prince de (1692-1740)], 1723 January 9 (Box 1)
    - Condé, Louis Joseph de Bourbon, prince de (1736-1818) (Box 1)
    - Coppée, François (1842-1908) (Box 1)
    - Coquelin, Constant (1841-1909) (Box 1)
    - D'Anvers, Caleb (Box 1)
    - Daudet, Alphonse (1840-1897) (Box 1)
    - [de Bullion, Claude]
    - [D'Étigny, Antoine Mégret (1719-1767)], 1765-1766 (Box 1)
    - Diane, de France (1538-1619)
    - Doguereau, Jean-Pierre (1774-1826) (Box 1)
    - Du Barry, Jeanne Bécu, comtesse (1743-1793)
    - [Dubreton, Jean-Louis], 1618 (Box 1)
    - [Duchesnay, Pierre?], 1714 May 28 (Box 1)
    - Dumas, Mathieu, comte (1753-1837) (Box 1)
    - [Dupas], 1810 (Box 1)
    - [Epernon, Jean-Louis de Nogaret de La Valette, duc d' (1592-1661)], 1652 (Box 1)
    - [Este, Anne de', Duchesse de Nemours], 1593 November 9 (Box 1)
    - [Estrades, Abbe J. F.], 1680 (Box 1)
    - Estrées, François Annibal de Coeuvres, Maréchal d' (1573-1670) (Box 1)
    - Estrées, Jean, duc d' (1624-1707) (Box 1)
    - Fitzjames, Charles de Fitzjames, duc de (1712-1787) (Box 1)
    - Fleury, André Hercule de (1653-1743) (Box 1)
    - Fontenelle, M. de (Bernard Le Bovier) (1657-1757) (Box 1)
    - Fouché, Joseph, duc d'Otrante (1759-1820) (Box 1)
    - Francis I, Holy Roman Emperor (1708-1765) (Box 1)
    - Francis I, King of France (1494-1547)
    - Frederick II, King of Prussia (1712-1786) (Box 1)
    - Gesvres, François-Joachim-Bernard Potier, duc de (1692-1757) (Box 2)
    - Guise, Charles de, Cardinal de Lorraine (Box 2)
    - Guise, Claude de Lorraine, duc de (1496-1550)
    - [Hector], 1779, undated (Box 2)
    - Henry II, King of France (1519-1559)
    - Henry III, King of France (1551-1589)
    - Henry IV, King of France (1553-1610) (Box 2)
    - Hugo, Victor (1802-1885) (Box 2)
    - Isabel Clara Eugenia, Infanta of Spain (1566-1633) (Box 2)
    - Joseph Bonaparte, King of Spain (1768-1844) (Box 2)
    - [Joyeuse, Anne, duc de (1561-1587)], undated (Box 2)
    - [Joyeuse, Louis de Lorraine, duc de (1622-1654)], 1652 (Box 2)
    - Karl Joseph, Archbishop of Trier (1680-1715) (Box 2)
    - [La Cardonnie, le chevalier de], undated (Box 2)
    - La Chaise, François d'Aix de (1624-1709) (Box 2)
    - [Le Coat de Saint-Haouen], 1794 (Box 2)
    - La Condamine, Charles-Marie de (1701-1774) (Box 2)
    - [La Galissonnière], 1781 January 18 (Box 2)
    - [La Porte-Vezin, Paul-Jules, de], 1784 August 11 (Box 2)
    - La Rochejaquelein, Henri du Vergier, comte de (1772-1794) (Box 2)
    - [La Salle, Louis de Caillebot], 1620 (Box 2)
    - [La Vallette, Henri de], 1641 May 23 (Box 2)
    - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de (1757-1834)
    - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de (1757-1834), 1883 (Box 2)
      Documents concerning a statue commemorating Lafayette, La Puy, France
    - Langle, Paul Antoine Marie Fleuriot, vicomte de (1744-1787) (Box 2)
    - [Le Bègue, comte de], 1783 April 24 (Box 2)
    - Lebrun, Charles-François, duc de Plaisance (1739-1824) (Box 2)
    - Léopold I, Duke of Lorraine (1679-1729) (Box 2)
    - Lhermitte, Jean (1766-1826) (Box 2)
    - [L'Hospital, Louis de, marquis de Vitry], 1593 (Box 2)
    - Linné, Carl von (1707-1778) (Box 2)
    - Louis, Dauphin of France (1661-1711)
    - Louis, Dauphin of France (1729-1765)
    - Louis III, Prince of Condé (1668-1710)
    - Louis XII, King of France (1462-1515) (Box 2)
    - Louis XIII, King of France (1601-1643), 2 (Box 2)
    - Louis XIV, King of France (1638-1715) (Box 2)
    - Louis XV, King of France (1710-1774), 4 (Box 2)
      See also: Louis XVI
    - Louis XVI, King of France (1754-1793), 3 (Box 2)
      Includes Louis XV
    - Louis XVIII, King of France (1755-1824)
    - Louis Philippe, King of the French (1773-1850)
    - Louvois, François-Michel Le Tellier, marquis de (1641-1691), 2 (Box 2)
    - Luxembourg, François-Henri de Montmorency, duc de (1628-1695) (Box 2)
    - [Macarty-Macteigue], 1777 September 11 (Box 3)
    - Macon, G. (Gustave) (1865-1930) (Box 3)
    - Mahlmann, Siegfried August (1771-1826) (Box 3)
    - Maintenon, Madame de (Box 3)
    - Malesherbes, Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon de (1721-1794) (Box 3)
    - Mandelot, François de (1529-1588) (Box 3)
    - Marbot, Jean-Baptiste-Antoine-Marcelin, baron de (1782-1854) (Box 3)
    - Marguerite, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of Navarre (1492-1549)
    - Marie Adelaide, of Savoy, Duchess of Burgundy (1685-1712)
    - Marie Antoinette, Queen, consort of Louis XVI, King of France (1755-1793), [circa 1785] (Box 3)
      Documents concerning the Diamond Necklace Affair
    - Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France (1573-1642) (Box 3)
    - Marie Leszczyńska, Queen, consort of Louis XV, King of France (1703-1768) (Box 3)
    - Marie-Thérèse, Queen, consort of Louis XIV, King of France (1638-1683)
    - Marochetti, Carlo (Pietro Carlo Giovanni Battista), Baron (1805-1867) (Box 3)
    - Maupertuis (1698-1759) (Box 3)
    - Maurepas, Jean-Frédéric Phélypeaux, comte de (1701-1781) (Box 3)
    - Maury, Jean Siffrein (1746-1817) (Box 3)
    - Mayenne, Charles de Lorraine, Duc de (1554-1611)
    - Mazarin, Jules (1602-1661) (Box 3)
    - Meissonier, Jean Louis Ernest (1815-1891) (Box 3)
    - [Mesnard, Jean Damascène], 1707 November 17 (Box 3)
    - [Moissac, P. C.], 1782 August 26 (Box 3)
    - [Monteclerc], 1777 April 18 (Box 3)
    - [Montmorency], 1636 (Box 3)
    - Montmorency, Anne, duc de (1493-1567) (Box 3)
    - Montmorency, Henri, duc de (1595-1632)
    - [Montmorency, Marie de, abbess de Maubuisson], 1542 October 7 (Box 3)
    - Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly (1549-1623) (Box 3)
    - Napoleon I, Emperor of the French (1769-1821) (Box 3)
    - Necker, Jacques (1732-1804) (Box 3)
    - [Nieuil, Claude-Arnold Poute, marquis de (1730-1806)], 1789 August 5 (Box 3)
    - [Nilsson, Christine], undated (Box 3)
    - [Noailles], 1820 March 7 (Box 3)
    - Noailles, Adrien-Maurice, duc de (1678-1766) (Box 3)
    - [Noailles, Anne, duc de (died 1678)], 1646 (Box 3)
    - Noailles, Louis-Antoine de (1651-1729) (Box 3)
    - Orléans, Gaston, duc d' (1608-1660) (Box 3)
    - Orléans, Louis, duc d' (1703-1752) (Box 3)
    - Orléans, Louis Philippe, duc d' (1725-1785)
    - Orléans, Louis Philippe Joseph, duc d' (1747-1793) (Box 3)
    - Orléans, Marguerite de Lorraine, duchesse d' (1615-1672) (Box 3)
    - [Orves, Thomas d'], 1781 April 2 (Box 3)
    - Orvilliers, M. le comte d' (Louis Guillouet) (1708-1792)
    - Palloy, Pierre François (1755-1835) (Box 3)
    - Panizzi, Anthony, Sir (1797-1879) (Box 3)
    - Perkins, James Breck (1847-1910) (Box 3)
    - [Peytes de Montcabrié], 1829 November 8 (Box 3)
    - Philip II, King of Spain (1527-1598) (Box 3)
    - Poinsinet, Antoine Alexandre Henri (1735-1769) (Box 3)
    - [Polignac], 1741, 1757 (Box 3)
    - Pompadour, Jeanne Antoinette Poisson, marquise de (1721-1764) (Box 3)
    - Pontchartrain, Louis Phélypeaux, comte de (1643-1727) (Box 3)
    - Rabutin, François de (d. 1581?) (Box 3)
    - Retz, Jean François Paul de Gondi de (1613-1679) (Box 3)
    - Richelieu, Armand Jean du Plessis, duc de (1585-1642) (Box 3)
    - Rochambeau, Donatien Marie Joseph de Vimeur, vicomte de (1750-1813)
    - Rohan, Henri, duc de (1579-1638) (Box 3)
    - [Roquelaure, Gaston-Jean-Baptiste, duc de (1656-1738)], 1736 (Box 3)
    - Sartine, Antoine de, comte d'Alby (1729-1801) (Box 3)
    - Saurin, M. (Bernard-Joseph) (1706-1781) (Box 3)
    - Savoie, Marie-Joséphine-Louise de, comtesse de Provence (1753-1810)
    - Saxe, Maurice, comte de (1696-1750) (Box 3)
    - [Schlegel], 1849 August 10 (Box 3)
    - [Ségur], undated (Box 3)
    - [Serigny, Joseph Le Moyne, sieur de (1668-1723)], 1700 July 20 (Box 3)
    - Sicard, M. l'abbé (Roch Ambroise Cucurron) (1742-1822) (Box 3)
    - Sigourney, L. H. (Lydia Howard) (1791-1865) (Box 3)
    - Soubise, Charles de Rohan, prince de (1715-1787) (Box 3)
    - Staël, Madame de (Anne-Louise-Germaine) (1766-1817) (Box 3)
    - [Staël-Holstein, Erik Magnus, baron de (1749-1802)], 1784-1789 (Box 3)
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent (1754-1838) (Box 3)
    - Thémines, Pons de Lauzières, Marquis de (ca. 1553-1627) (Box 3)
    - Turenne, Henri de La Tour d'Auvergne, vicomte de (1611-1675), 2 (Box 3)
    - Turgot, Anne-Robert-Jacques, baron de l'Aulne (1727-1781) (Box 3)
    - Vaillant, Jean-Baptiste Philibert (1790-1872) (Box 3)
    - Vendôme, César de Bourbon, duc de (1594-1665)
    - Vendôme, Louis-Joseph, duc de (1654-1712) (Box 3)
    - Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de (1719-1787) (Box 3)
    - Vernet, Horace (1789-1863) (Box 3)
    - [Villeneuve], 1697 January 12 (Box 3)
    - Zola, Émile (1840-1902) (Box 3)
  - Historical Manuscripts, Unidentified
    - American, undated (Box 4)
    - Belgian, 1831 September 16
    - English, 1798 July 12 (Box 4)
    - French, before 1600 (Box 4)
    - French, 1600s; 2 (Box 4)
    - French, 1700-1770s; 2 (Box 4)
    - French, 1780s (Box 4)
    - French, 1790s (Box 4)
    - French, 1800s; 2 (Box 4)
    - French, 1810s (Box 4)
    - French, 1820s (Box 4)
    - French, 1830s (Box 4)
    - French, 1840s-1870s (Box 4)
    - French, undated (Box 4)
    - German, 1800s-1850s, undated (Box 4)
    - Italian, 1847, undated (Box 4)
  - Research Material
    - Engravings, undated
    - Notes and clippings, 1920s-circa 1960s, undated (Box 5)
    - Card files, 5 (Box 5)
    - Card files, 4 (Box 6)
    - Card files (Box 7)
  - Oversize
    - Anjou, François, duc d' (1554-1584), 2 (Box 9 Oversize)
    - [Bourbon, Francois de], 1593 August 15 (Box 9 Oversize)
    - [Bourbon, Louis Auguste de, duc du Maine (1670-1736)], undated (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Bourbon, Louis Jean-Marie de, duc de Penthièvre (1725-1793) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Catherine de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of France (1519-1589) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles, d'Orléans (1394-1465) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles V, King of France (1338-1380) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles VI, King of France (1368-1422) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles VIII, King of France (1470-1498) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles IX, King of France (1550-1574) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Charles X, King of France (1757-1836) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Clèves, Marie de (1426-1487) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Condé, Louis, prince de (1530-1569) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Condé, Louis, prince de (1621-1686) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - [Condé, Louis Henri de Bourbon, prince de (1692-1740)], 1729 December 2 (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Condé, Louis Joseph de Bourbon, prince de (1736-1818) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - [de Bullion, Claude], 1625 (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Diane, de France (1538-1619) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Du Barry, Jeanne Bécu, comtesse (1743-1793) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Francis I, King of France (1494-1547), 4 (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Guise, Claude de Lorraine, duc de (1496-1550) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Henry II, King of France (1519-1559) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Henry III, King of France (1551-1589) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Henry IV, King of France (1553-1610) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de (1757-1834) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Louis, Dauphin of France (1661-1711) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Louis, Dauphin of France (1729-1765) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Louis III, Prince of Condé (1668-1710) (Box 9 Oversize)
    - Louis XII, King of France (1462-1515) (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis XIII, King of France (1601-1643), 3 (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis XIV, King of France (1638-1715), 4 (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis XV, King of France (1710-1774), 2 (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis XVI, King of France (1754-1793), 2 (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis XVIII, King of France (1755-1824) (Box 10 Oversize)
    - Louis Philippe, King of the French (1773-1850) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Maintenon, Madame de (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Marguerite, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of Navarre (1492-1549) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Marie Adelaide, of Savoy, Duchess of Burgundy (1685-1712) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France (1573-1642), 2 (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Marie-Thérèse, Queen, consort of Louis XIV, King of France (1638-1683) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Mayenne, Charles de Lorraine, Duc de (1554-1611) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Montmorency, Henri, duc de (1595-1632) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Orléans, Gaston, duc d' (1608-1660) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Orléans, Louis Philippe, duc d' (1725-1785) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Orvilliers, M. le comte d' (Louis Guillouet) (1708-1792) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Rochambeau, Donatien Marie Joseph de Vimeur, vicomte de (1750-1813) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Savoie, Marie-Joséphine-Louise de, comtesse de Provence (1753-1810) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Soubise, Charles de Rohan, prince de (1715-1787) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Vendôme, César de Bourbon, duc de (1594-1665) (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, Belgian, 1831 September 16 (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, before 1600 (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1700-1770s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1790s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1800s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1810s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1820s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Unidentified, French, 1830s (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Research Material, Engravings, undated (Box 11 Oversize)
    - Research Material, Notes and Clippings, 1920s-circa 1960s, undated (Box 11 Oversize)
- July 2005 Acquisitions, 1777-1920s; 7
  Arranged chronologically.